Last year, I told you the story, in seven minutes, of Project Orion,
حكيت لكم العام الماضي قصة مشروع أوريون في سبع دقائق
which was this very implausible technology
والتي كانت التقنية المستحيلة جدا
that technically could have worked,
والتي كان من الممكن تقنيا أن تعمل
but it had this one-year political window where it could have happened.
ولكن كان عليها ضغوط سياسية لتعمل في سنة
So it didn't happen. It was a dream that did not happen.
لذا لم تنفذ. كانت حلما لم يحدث
This year I'm going to tell you the story of the birth of digital computing.
هذا العام سأقص عليكم قصة مولد الحاسبات الرقمية
This was a perfect introduction.
وقد كانت هذه مقدمة مثالية
And it's a story that did work. It did happen,
وهي قصة نفذت. وقد حدثت
and the machines are all around us.
والآلات من حولنا
And it was a technology that was inevitable.
وقد كانت تقنية لا مفر منها
If the people I'm going to tell you the story about,
لو أن الناس الذين سأتحدث عنهم
if they hadn't done it, somebody else would have.
لو أنهم لم يفعلوها، لفعلها قوم آخرون
So, it was sort of the right idea at the right time.
فقد كانت هذه الفكرة الصحيحة في الوقت الصحيح
This is Barricelli's universe. This is the universe we live in now.
هذا كون بيرسيلي. هذا هو الكون الذي نعيش فيه الآن
It's the universe in which these machines
إنه الكون الذي تعمل به هذه الآلات
are now doing all these things, including changing biology.
كل هذه الأمور، بما فيها تغيير الأحياء
I'm starting the story with the first atomic bomb at Trinity,
سأبدأ القصة من أول قنبلة نووية في ترينيتي
which was the Manhattan Project. It was a little bit like TED:
والتي كانت تدعى بمشروع مانهاتن. كان إلى حد ما شبيها بتيد
it brought a whole lot of very smart people together.
لقد جمع الكثير من الأذكياء معا
And three of the smartest people were
وكان من أذكى ثلاثة
Stan Ulam, Richard Feynman and John von Neumann.
ستان أولام، ريتشارد فينمان و جون فون نيومان
And it was Von Neumann who said, after the bomb,
وقد كان فون نيومان من قال، بعد القنبلة
he was working on something much more important than bombs:
أنه يعمل على شيء أكثر أهمية من القنبلة
he's thinking about computers.
إنه يفكر في الحاسبات
So, he wasn't only thinking about them; he built one. This is the machine he built.
لم يكن يفكر فيها فحسب؛ لقد بنى آلة. هذه هي الآلة التي بناها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He built this machine,
لقد بنى هذه الآلة
and we had a beautiful demonstration of how this thing really works,
ولقد حصلنا على عرض جميل عن كيفية عملها
with these little bits. And it's an idea that goes way back.
مع هذه الأجزاء الصغيرة. وهي فكرة تعود إلى ماضي بعيد
The first person to really explain that
إن أول شخص يشرح ذلك
was Thomas Hobbes, who, in 1651,
كان توماس هوبز، في عام 1651
explained how arithmetic and logic are the same thing,
شرح كيف أن الحساب والمنطق هما نقس الشيء
and if you want to do artificial thinking and artificial logic,
وأنك لو أردت أن نصنع التفكير الاصطناعي والمنطق الاصطناعي
you can do it all with arithmetic.
يمكنك صنعه بالحساب
He said you needed addition and subtraction.
قال أنك تحتاج إلى الجمع والطرح
Leibniz, who came a little bit later -- this is 1679 --
ليبينز، والذي أتى بعد ذلك بقليل -- هذا في 1969 -ـ
showed that you didn't even need subtraction.
أوضح أنك لا تحتاج حتى إلى الطرح
You could do the whole thing with addition.
يمكنك صنع الأمر برمته بالجمع
Here, we have all the binary arithmetic and logic
هنا نجد كل الحساب والمنطق الزوجي
that drove the computer revolution.
الذي قاد ثورة الحاسب
And Leibniz was the first person to really talk about building such a machine.
وليبينز كان أول شخص يتحدث عن بناء هذه الآلة
He talked about doing it with marbles,
لقد تحدث عن صنعها بالبرجون
having gates and what we now call shift registers,
مع بوابات وما نسميه الآن سجلات التحول
where you shift the gates, drop the marbles down the tracks.
حيث تحول البوابة، وتسقط البرجونة على الطريق
And that's what all these machines are doing,
وهذا ما تقوم به جميع هذه الآلات
except, instead of doing it with marbles,
إلا أنها بدلا عن استخدام البرجون
they're doing it with electrons.
تستخدم الإليكترونات
And then we jump to Von Neumann, 1945,
ثم نقفز إلى فون نيومن، 1945
when he sort of reinvents the whole same thing.
حين قام نوعا ما بإعادة اختراع الشيء نفسه بالكامل
And 1945, after the war, the electronics existed
و1945، بعد الحرب، الإليكترونيات كانت موجودة
to actually try and build such a machine.
لمحاولة بناء مثل هذه الآلة في الواقع
So June 1945 -- actually, the bomb hasn't even been dropped yet --
إذا يونيو 1945. لم تكن القنبلة قد أسقطت بعد
and Von Neumann is putting together all the theory to actually build this thing,
وفون نيومن بدأ بجمع كل النظريات اللازمة لبناء هذا الشيء
which also goes back to Turing,
والذي يعود أيضا لتورنج
who, before that, gave the idea that you could do all this
الذي، قبل ذلك، قدم فكرة أنك تستطيع فعل كل هذا
with a very brainless, little, finite state machine,
بجهاز محدود الحالات
just reading a tape in and reading a tape out.
يقرأ من شريط ويكتب في شريط
The other sort of genesis of what Von Neumann did
والعبقرية الأخرى التي قام بها فون نيومن
was the difficulty of how you would predict the weather.
هي صعوبة كيفية التنبؤ بالطقس
Lewis Richardson saw how you could do this with a cellular array of people,
ليويس ريتشاردسن رأى كيف يمكنك القيام بذلك بمجموعة من الناس
giving them each a little chunk, and putting it together.
بإعطاء كل منهم جزء، ثم جمعها
Here, we have an electrical model illustrating a mind having a will,
هنا لدينا تمثيل كهربائي لعقل له دافع
but capable of only two ideas.
ولكنه قادر فقط على فكرتين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's really the simplest computer.
وهذا في الواقع أبسط حاسب
It's basically why you need the qubit,
وهو سبب احتياجنا لخانة الترتيب
because it only has two ideas.
لأنها فقط تحمل فكرتين
And you put lots of those together,
وبجمع العديد منها معا
you get the essentials of the modern computer:
تحصل على أساسيات الحاسبات الحديثة
the arithmetic unit, the central control, the memory,
وحدة الحساب، التحكم المركزي، الذاكرة
the recording medium, the input and the output.
وسط التسجيل، والإدخال والإخراج
But, there's one catch. This is the fatal -- you know,
ولكن، هناك مشكلة واحدة. وهي قاتلة -- كما تعلمون
we saw it in starting these programs up.
وجدناها حين بدأ هذه البرامج
The instructions which govern this operation
التعليمات التي تحكم هذه العملية
must be given in absolutely exhaustive detail.
يجب أن تقدم بالتفصيل الممل
So, the programming has to be perfect, or it won't work.
فالبرامج يجب أن تكون متقنة وإلا لن تعمل
If you look at the origins of this,
ولو نظرنا إلى أصول هذا
the classic history sort of takes it all back to the ENIAC here.
التاريخ التقليدي يعيدها إلى الإنياك
But actually, the machine I'm going to tell you about,
ولكن الآلة التي سأحدثكم هنا في الواقع
the Institute for Advanced Study machine, which is way up there,
معهد آلة الدراسة العظمى، وهو في الأعلى هنا
really should be down there. So, I'm trying to revise history,
في الواقع يجب أن يكون في الأسفل هناك. فأنا أحاول مراجعة التاريخ
and give some of these guys more credit than they've had.
وأعطي بعض هؤلاء الأشخاص تشريفا أكثر مما حصلوا عليه
Such a computer would open up universes,
مثل هذا الحاسب سيفتح أكوان
which are, at the present, outside the range of any instruments.
والتي تقع في الوقت الحالي خارج نطاق الأدوات
So it opens up a whole new world, and these people saw it.
لذا فهي تفتح عالم جديد كليا، وفد رأى هؤلاء الأشخاص ذلك
The guy who was supposed to build this machine
الشخص الذي كان من المفترض أن يصنع هذه الآلة
was the guy in the middle, Vladimir Zworykin, from RCA.
كان الرجل المتوسط، فالديمير زيوركن من شركة آر سي إيه
RCA, in probably one of the lousiest business decisions
آر سي إيه، في أسوء قرار تجاري
of all time, decided not to go into computers.
على الإطلاق، قررت عدم الدخول في الحاسبات
But the first meetings, November 1945, were at RCA's offices.
ولكن الاجتماع الأول، نوفمبر 1945، كان في مكتب آر سي إيه
RCA started this whole thing off, and said, you know,
آر سي إيه هي من أطلق هذا الأمر برمته، ثم قالت، أتعلمون
televisions are the future, not computers.
التلفاز هو المستقبل، وليست الحاسبات
The essentials were all there --
الأساسيات كانت جميعها متوفرة
all the things that make these machines run.
كل ما يجعل هذه الآلات تعمل
Von Neumann, and a logician, and a mathematician from the army
فون نيومن، ومنطقي ورياضي من الجيش
put this together. Then, they needed a place to build it.
جمعوا هذا. ومن ثم احتاجوا إلى مكان لبنائه
When RCA said no, that's when they decided to build it in Princeton,
حين قالت آر سي إيه لا، حينها قرروا بنائه في برينستون
where Freeman works at the Institute.
حيث يعمل فريمن في المعهد
That's where I grew up as a kid.
هنا نشأت في طفولتي
That's me, that's my sister Esther, who's talked to you before,
هذا أنا، تلك أختي إسثر، والتي تحدثت معكم مسبقا
so we both go back to the birth of this thing.
فكلانا يعود إلى مولد هذا الشيء
That's Freeman, a long time ago,
ذلك فريمن، منذ زمن بعيد
and that was me.
وكان ذلك أنا
And this is Von Neumann and Morgenstern,
وهذا فون نيومن ومورجنستيرن
who wrote the "Theory of Games."
الذي كتب نظرية الألعاب
All these forces came together there, in Princeton.
كل هذه القوى تجمعت هناك، في برينستون
Oppenheimer, who had built the bomb.
أوبنهيمر، الذي بنى القنبلة
The machine was actually used mainly for doing bomb calculations.
الآلة كانت تستخدم عموما لحسابات القنابل
And Julian Bigelow, who took
وجوليان بيجالو، الذي أخذ
Zworkykin's place as the engineer, to actually figure out, using electronics,
مكانة المهندس الذي تعرف على، باستخدام الإلكترونيات
how you would build this thing. The whole gang of people who came to work on this,
كيف تبني هذا الشيء. كامل المجموعة التي عملت على هذا
and women in front, who actually did most of the coding, were the first programmers.
النساء في الأمام، اللاتي قمن بمعظم البرمجة، كانوا أول المبرمجين
These were the prototype geeks, the nerds.
هؤلاء هم أوائل التقنيين
They didn't fit in at the Institute.
لم يتأقلموا في المعهد
This is a letter from the director, concerned about --
هذه رسالة من المدير، قلقا إزاء
"especially unfair on the matter of sugar."
عدم المساواة في ما يخص السكر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You can read the text.
يمكنكم قراءة النص
This is hackers getting in trouble for the first time.
هذه أول حادثة يتورط فيها المبرمجين
(Laughter).
(ضحك)
These were not theoretical physicists.
هؤلاء ليسوا فيزيائيين نظريين
They were real soldering-gun type guys, and they actually built this thing.
كانوا يعملون بمسدسات اللحام الحقيقية، وقاموا ببناء هذا الشيء حقيقة
And we take it for granted now, that each of these machines
ونحن نتعامل معه كالمسلمات أن كل من هذه الأجهزة
has billions of transistors, doing billions of cycles per second without failing.
لها بلايين الترانزستورات، تقوم ببلايين الدورات في الثانية دون عطل
They were using vacuum tubes, very narrow, sloppy techniques
كانوا يستخدمون الأنابيب المفرغة، أساليب ضيقة وقذرة
to get actually binary behavior out of these radio vacuum tubes.
للحصول على سلوك ثنائي من هذه الأنابيب المفرغة
They actually used 6J6, the common radio tube,
لقد استخدموا الأنابيب المفرغة المتاحة للراديو
because they found they were more reliable than the more expensive tubes.
لأنهم وجدوا أنها أكثر فعالية من الأنابيب الغالية
And what they did at the Institute was publish every step of the way.
وكانوا في المعهد ينشرون كل خطواتهم
Reports were issued, so that this machine was cloned
التقارير كانت تصدر، لتستنسخ هذه الآلة
at 15 other places around the world.
في 15 موقع آخر حول العالم
And it really was. It was the original microprocessor.
وقد كان. لقد كان المعالج الأصلي
All the computers now are copies of that machine.
جميع الحاسبات اليوم هي نسخ من تلك الآلة
The memory was in cathode ray tubes --
الذاكرة كانت مصابيح الأشعة المهبطية
a whole bunch of spots on the face of the tube --
مجموعة من البقع على سطح الأنبوب
very, very sensitive to electromagnetic disturbances.
حساسة جدا للتأثيرات الكهرومغناطيسية
So, there's 40 of these tubes,
فهناك 40 من هذه الأنابيب
like a V-40 engine running the memory.
كمحرك في 40 يدير الذاكرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The input and the output was by teletype tape at first.
الإدخال والإخراج كانا عن طريق شريط البرقيات في البداية
This is a wire drive, using bicycle wheels.
هذا محرك سلكي، يستخدم إطارات دراجة
This is the archetype of the hard disk that's in your machine now.
هذا هو النموذج الأول للقرص الصلب في جهازك الآن
Then they switched to a magnetic drum.
ثم حولوا إلى أسطوانة ممغنطة
This is modifying IBM equipment,
هذا تعديل على أدوات آي بي إم
which is the origins of the whole data-processing industry, later at IBM.
وهذه هي الأصول لصناعة معالجة البيانات لاحقا في آي بي إم
And this is the beginning of computer graphics.
وهذه بداية رسومات الحاسبات
The "Graph'g-Beam Turn On." This next slide,
في الشريحة القادمة
that's the -- as far as I know -- the first digital bitmap display, 1954.
تلك هي -- على حد علمي -- أول عارض رقمي 1954
So, Von Neumann was already off in a theoretical cloud,
إذا، فون نيومن كان محلقا في سحابة نظرية
doing abstract sorts of studies of how you could build
يقوم بدراسات تجريدية عن كيفية صناعة
reliable machines out of unreliable components.
آلة يعتمد عليها من مكونات غير معتمدة
Those guys drinking all the tea with sugar in it
هؤلاء الرجال الذين يشربون كل الشاي بالسكر
were writing in their logbooks, trying to get this thing to work, with all
كانوا يكتبون في مدوناتهم في محاولة لجعل هذا الشيء يعمل بكل تلك
these 2,600 vacuum tubes that failed half the time.
الأنابيب المفرغة الـ 2600 التي كانت تعطب نصف الوقت
And that's what I've been doing, this last six months, is going through the logs.
وهذا ما كنت أعمل عليه في الأشهر الست الماضية، تصفح المذكرات
"Running time: two minutes. Input, output: 90 minutes."
مدة التشغيل: دقيقتين. إدخال، إخراج: 90 دقيقة
This includes a large amount of human error.
هذه تتضمن كمية كبيرة من الأخطاء البشرية
So they are always trying to figure out, what's machine error? What's human error?
لذا فهما دوما يحاولون اكتشاف ما هي الأخطاء البشرية؟ وما هي أخطاء الآلة؟
What's code, what's hardware?
ما هو في البرنامج؟ وما هو في الأجهزة؟
That's an engineer gazing at tube number 36,
هذا مهندس يحدق على الأنبوب رقم 36
trying to figure out why the memory's not in focus.
محاولا اكتشاف سبب عدم تركز الذاكرة
He had to focus the memory -- seems OK.
عليه تركيز الذاكرة -- تبدو سليمة
So, he had to focus each tube just to get the memory up and running,
فأضطر إلى تركيز كل أنبوب فقط لإعادة تشغيل الذاكرة
let alone having, you know, software problems.
ناهيك عن، كما تعلمون، مشاكل البرامج
"No use, went home." (Laughter)
لا فائدة، عدت إلى المنزل (ضحك)
"Impossible to follow the damn thing, where's a directory?"
يستحيل متابعة هذا الشيء اللعين، أين الدليل؟
So, already, they're complaining about the manuals:
إذا قد بدؤوا الشكوى عن الأدلة
"before closing down in disgust ... "
قبل الإغلاق في اشمئزاز
"The General Arithmetic: Operating Logs."
الحسابات العامة -- سجلات التشغيل
Burning lots of midnight oil.
السهر لليالي طويلة
"MANIAC," which became the acronym for the machine,
مانياك، الذي أصبح كنية الآلة
Mathematical and Numerical Integrator and Calculator, "lost its memory."
دامج وحاسب الرياضيات والأعداد، فقد قي الذاكرة
"MANIAC regained its memory, when the power went off." "Machine or human?"
مانياك استعاد ذاكرته حين قطعت الكهرباء، آلة أم بشر؟
"Aha!" So, they figured out it's a code problem.
آها! إذا فقد اكتشفوا أنها مشكلة برمجية
"Found trouble in code, I hope."
وجدنا مشكلة في البرنامج، أرجو ذلك
"Code error, machine not guilty."
خطأ برمجي، الآلة غير مذنبة
"Damn it, I can be just as stubborn as this thing."
اللعنة، يمكنني أن أكون بعند هذه الآلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And the dawn came." So they ran all night.
وأتى الفجر. إذا فقد عملوا طوال الليل
Twenty-four hours a day, this thing was running, mainly running bomb calculations.
عمل هذا الشيء 24 ساعة يوميا، تعمل على حسابات القنابل في الأغلب
"Everything up to this point is wasted time." "What's the use? Good night."
كل شيء حتى هذه اللحظة مضيعة للوقت. ما الفائدة؟ طابت ليلتكم
"Master control off. The hell with it. Way off." (Laughter)
التحكم الرئيسي مطفئ. فليذهب إلى الجحيم. بعيدا جدا. (ضحك)
"Something's wrong with the air conditioner --
هناك خطأ ما في مكيف الهواء
smell of burning V-belts in the air."
رائحة سيور محروقة
"A short -- do not turn the machine on."
التماس -- لا تشغلوا الآلة
"IBM machine putting a tar-like substance on the cards. The tar is from the roof."
آلة آي بي إم تضع مادة تشبه القطران على السيارات. القطران من السقف
So they really were working under tough conditions.
فقد كانوا يعملون فعلا تحت ظروف قاسية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here, "A mouse has climbed into the blower
هنا، "تسلق فئر إلى داخل التهوية
behind the regulator rack, set blower to vibrating. Result: no more mouse."
خلف دولاب المنظم، ضبطت التهوية على الهزاز، النتيجة: لم يعد هناك فأر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Here lies mouse. Born: ?. Died: 4:50 a.m., May 1953."
هنا دفن فأر. ولد؟ مات 4:50 صباحا، مايو 1953
There's an inside joke someone has penciled in:
هذه طرفة داخلية كتبها أحدهم
"Here lies Marston Mouse."
هنا دفن الفأر مارستون
If you're a mathematician, you get that,
إذا كنت رياضيا، ستفهم
because Marston was a mathematician who
لأن مارستون كان رياضيا قد
objected to the computer being there.
اعترض على وجود الحاسب هناك
"Picked a lightning bug off the drum." "Running at two kilocycles."
التقطت حباحب من الاسطوانة، تعمل على ألفي دورة
That's two thousand cycles per second --
ألفي دورة في الثانية
"yes, I'm chicken" -- so two kilocycles was slow speed.
نعم، أنا جبان -- إذا ألفي دورة كانت سرعة بطيئة
The high speed was 16 kilocycles.
السرعة العالية كانت 16 ألف دورة
I don't know if you remember a Mac that was 16 Megahertz,
لا أعرف إن كنتم تذكرون، الماك كان يعمل على 16 مليون دورة
that's slow speed.
تلك كانت سرعة بطيئة
"I have now duplicated both results.
قمت الآن بتكرار كلا النتيجتين
How will I know which is right, assuming one result is correct?
كيف سأعرف أيهما الصحيح، بافتراض أن أحدهم صحيح؟
This now is the third different output.
هذا الآن هو المخرج الثالث
I know when I'm licked."
أعرف حين أكون مخدوعا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"We've duplicated errors before."
لقد كررنا الأخطاء من قبل
"Machine run, fine. Code isn't."
الآلة تعمل بكفاءة، البرنامج لا
"Only happens when the machine is running."
فقط يحدث والآلة تعمل
And sometimes things are okay.
وأحيانا تكون الأمور سليمة
"Machine a thing of beauty, and a joy forever." "Perfect running."
الآلة قطعة جمالية، ومتعة أبدية. تعمل بامتياز
"Parting thought: when there's bigger and better errors, we'll have them."
حين تحدث أخطاء أكبر سنجدهم
So, nobody was supposed to know they were actually designing bombs.
فلم يكن من المفترض أن يعرف أحد أنهم يصممون قنابل
They're designing hydrogen bombs. But someone in the logbook,
إنهم يصممون قنابل هيدروجينية. إلا أن أحدهم في المدونة
late one night, finally drew a bomb.
متأخرا في أحد الليالي، رسم أخيرا قنبلة
So, that was the result. It was Mike,
فكانت تلك هي النتيجة، لقد كان مايك
the first thermonuclear bomb, in 1952.
أول قنبلة حرارية نووية في 1952
That was designed on that machine,
التي صممت على تلك الآلة
in the woods behind the Institute.
في الغابات خلف المعهد
So Von Neumann invited a whole gang of weirdos
إذا فون نيومن دعا مجموعة من الغرباء
from all over the world to work on all these problems.
من حول العالم للعمل على كل تلك المشاكل
Barricelli, he came to do what we now call, really, artificial life,
بيرسيلي، أتى ليعمل على ما نسميه الآن، حقا، الحياة الصناعية
trying to see if, in this artificial universe --
محاولا أن يجد إذا، في هذا الكون الصناعي
he was a viral-geneticist, way, way, way ahead of his time.
كان عالم فيروسي -- متقدما جدا جدا حدا على زمنه
He's still ahead of some of the stuff that's being done now.
لا يزال متقدما على بعض الأشياء التي نعملها الآن
Trying to start an artificial genetic system running in the computer.
محاولا بدء نظام جيني صناعي على الحاسب
Began -- his universe started March 3, '53.
بدء -- بدء كونه في 3 مارس 53
So it's almost exactly -- it's 50 years ago next Tuesday, I guess.
فهي تقريبا مطابقة -- إنها 50 عام من الثلاثاء القادم على ما أعتقد
And he saw everything in terms of --
وقد تصور كل شيء من حيث
he could read the binary code straight off the machine.
إنه يستطيع قراءة الشفرة الثنائية من الآلة مباشرة
He had a wonderful rapport.
كان لديه تقريرا رائعا
Other people couldn't get the machine running. It always worked for him.
الآخرون لم يتمكنوا من جعل الآلة تعمل. وقد عملت له دوما
Even errors were duplicated.
حتى الأخطاء كانت تتكرر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Dr. Barricelli claims machine is wrong, code is right."
د. بيرسيلي يدعي أن الآلة مخطئة، البرنامج صحيح
So he designed this universe, and ran it.
فقد صمم هذا الكون، وأداره
When the bomb people went home, he was allowed in there.
حين ذهب قوم القنبلة إلى المنزل، كان يسمح له بالدخول
He would run that thing all night long, running these things,
يقوم بتشغيل ذلك الشيء طوال الليل، تشغل تلك الأشياء
if anybody remembers Stephen Wolfram,
إذا تذكر أحدكم ستيفن ولفارم
who reinvented this stuff.
الذي أعاد اختراع هذا الشيء
And he published it. It wasn't locked up and disappeared.
ونشرها. لم تكن مخفية
It was published in the literature.
لقد نشرت في الكتابات
"If it's that easy to create living organisms, why not create a few yourself?"
إذا كانت صناعة الكائنات الحية بتلك السهولة، لما لا تصنع بعضها بنفسك
So, he decided to give it a try,
فقرر تجربة ذلك
to start this artificial biology going in the machines.
لبدء هذه الحياة الصناعية داخل الآلة
And he found all these, sort of --
وقد وجد كل هذه، نوعا ما
it was like a naturalist coming in
كانت مثل دخول عالم طبيعي
and looking at this tiny, 5,000-byte universe,
ونظر إلى الكون الصغير ذو 5000 بايت
and seeing all these things happening
ورؤية كل تلك الأشياء تحدث
that we see in the outside world, in biology.
التي نراها في العالم الخارجي، في الأحياء
This is some of the generations of his universe.
هذه بعض الأجيال من عالمه
But they're just going to stay numbers;
ولكنها ستبقى أرقام
they're not going to become organisms.
لن تصبح كائنات
They have to have something.
إنها تحتاج إلى شيء
You have a genotype and you have to have a phenotype.
لديك المورث والنمط الظاهري
They have to go out and do something. And he started doing that,
عليهما الخروج وعمل شيء. وقد بدء بفعل ذلك
started giving these little numerical organisms things they could play with --
بدأ بإعطاء هذه الكائنات أشياء رقمية صغيرة يمكنهم اللعب بها
playing chess with other machines and so on.
لعب الشطرنج مع الآلات أخرى وما إلى ذلك
And they did start to evolve.
وقد بدأت بالتطور
And he went around the country after that.
وقد جاب البلاد بعد ذلك
Every time there was a new, fast machine, he started using it,
كلما ظهرت آلة جديدة سريعة، بدأ باستخدامها
and saw exactly what's happening now.
ورأى تماما ما يحدث الآن
That the programs, instead of being turned off -- when you quit the program,
أن البرامج، عوضا عن إطفائها -- حين تخرج من البرنامج
you'd keep running
ستبقى مفعلة
and, basically, all the sorts of things like Windows is doing,
و، مبدئيا، كل الأمور التي يقوم بها ويندوز
running as a multi-cellular organism on many machines,
يعمل ككائن متعدد الخلايا على عدة آلات
he envisioned all that happening.
لقد تخيل حدوث كل ذلك
And he saw that evolution itself was an intelligent process.
وقد تخيل أن التطور ذاته عملية ذكية
It wasn't any sort of creator intelligence,
لم تكن أي نوع من ذكاء الصانع
but the thing itself was a giant parallel computation
بل الشيء نفسه كان حاسب متوازي عملاق
that would have some intelligence.
لديه نوع من الذكاء
And he went out of his way to say
وقد تعدى مسؤولياته ليقول
that he was not saying this was lifelike,
أنه لا يدعي أن هذه مثل الحياة
or a new kind of life.
أو أنها نوع جديد من الحياة
It just was another version of the same thing happening.
ولكنها نسخة جديدة من نفس الشيء
And there's really no difference between what he was doing in the computer
وأنه لا يوجد أي اختلاف حقيقي بين ما يقوم به على الحاسب
and what nature did billions of years ago.
وما قامت به الطبيعة منذ بلايين السنين
And could you do it again now?
وهل تستطيع إعادة ذلك الآن؟
So, when I went into these archives looking at this stuff, lo and behold,
فحين تعمقت في هذا الأرشيف لمحت
the archivist came up one day, saying,
أن الأرشيف ظهر في أحد الأيام، يقول
"I think we found another box that had been thrown out."
أعتقد أننا وجدنا صندوقا آخرا قد رمي بالخارج
And it was his universe on punch cards.
وقد كان كونه على كروت مثقوبة
So there it is, 50 years later, sitting there -- sort of suspended animation.
ها هو ذا، بعد 50 عام، يجلس هناك. في نوع من الجمود الحركي
That's the instructions for running --
هذه أوامر التشغيل
this is actually the source code
هذا في الواقع نص البرنامج
for one of those universes,
لأحد هذه الأكوان
with a note from the engineers
معها ملاحظة من المهندس
saying they're having some problems.
تقول أن بها بعض المشاكل
"There must be something about this code that you haven't explained yet."
لابد أن هناك شيء في هذا البرنامج لم تشرحه بعد
And I think that's really the truth. We still don't understand
وأعتقد أن تلك هي الحقيقة. فلازلنا لا نفهم
how these very simple instructions can lead to increasing complexity.
كيف أن هذه الأوامر البسيطة تقود إلى تعقيد متزايد
What's the dividing line between
ما هو الخط الفاصل بين
when that is lifelike and when it really is alive?
شبيه الحياة وحين يكون حيا حقا؟
These cards, now, thanks to me showing up, are being saved.
هذه الكروت، الآن، بفضل ظهوري، ستحفظ
And the question is, should we run them or not?
والسؤال، هل نشغلها أم لا؟
You know, could we get them running?
تعلمون، هل نستطيع تشغيلها؟
Do you want to let it loose on the Internet?
هل نود فلتها على الإنترنت؟
These machines would think they --
هذه الآلات قد تعتقد أنها
these organisms, if they came back to life now --
هذه الكائنات، لو عادت إلى الحياة الآن
whether they've died and gone to heaven, there's a universe.
هل ماتت وذهب إلى السماء، هناك كون
My laptop is 10 thousand million times
فجهازي بحجم 10 آلاف مليون
the size of the universe that they lived in when Barricelli quit the project.
مرة من الكون الذي عاشوا فيه حين ترك بيرسيلي المشروع
He was thinking far ahead, to
كان يفكر بعيدا
how this would really grow into a new kind of life.
لكيفية نمو هذا في الواقع إلى نوع جديد من الحياة
And that's what's happening!
وهذا ما يحدث
When Juan Enriquez told us about
حين حدثنا جون إينريكيز عن
these 12 trillion bits being transferred back and forth,
هذا الـ 12 تريليون بت المتنقلة ذهابا وإيابا
of all this genomics data going to the proteomics lab,
بكل بيانات هذه الجينات إلى معمل البروتيوميات
that's what Barricelli imagined:
هذا ما تخيله بيرسيلي
that this digital code in these machines
أن هذا البرنامج الرقمي في هذه الآلات
is actually starting to code --
ستبدأ حقيقة ببرمجة
it already is coding from nucleic acids.
بل إنها تبرمج من أحماض نووية
We've been doing that since, you know, since we started PCR
نحن نعمل ذلك منذ، تعلمون، منذ أن بدئنا
and synthesizing small strings of DNA.
وتصنيع خيوط صغيرة من الحمض النووي
And real soon, we're actually going to be synthesizing the proteins,
وقريبا جدا سنتمكن من تصنيع البروتينات
and, like Steve showed us, that just opens an entirely new world.
وكما أوضح ستيف، هذا يفتح عوالم جديدة تماما
It's a world that Von Neumann himself envisioned.
إنه عالم تخيله فون نيومن ذاته
This was published after he died: his sort of unfinished notes
لقد نشر هذا بعد موته: ملاحظاته غير المنتهية
on self-reproducing machines,
عن الآلات ذاتية الاستنساخ
what it takes to get the machines sort of jump-started
ما تحتاجه الآلات لبدء العمل
to where they begin to reproduce.
إلى حيث يمكنها التكاثر
It took really three people:
لقد عمل ثلاث أشخاص
Barricelli had the concept of the code as a living thing;
بيرسيلي كانت لديه فكرة البرنامج ككائن حي
Von Neumann saw how you could build the machines --
فون نيومن تصور كيف يمكن بناء الآلة
that now, last count, four million
والتي هي الآن، حسب آخر إحصائية، 4 مليون
of these Von Neumann machines is built every 24 hours;
آلة من هذه الآلات تصنع كل 24 ساعة
and Julian Bigelow, who died 10 days ago --
وجوليان بيجالو، الذي مات منذ 10 أيام
this is John Markoff's obituary for him --
هذا رثاء جون ماركوف له
he was the important missing link,
كان الرابط المهم الناقص
the engineer who came in
المهندس الذي أتى
and knew how to put those vacuum tubes together and make it work.
وعرف كيف بجمع هذه الأنابيب المفرغة وجعلها تعمل
And all our computers have, inside them,
وكل حاسباتنا تحوي، داخلها
the copies of the architecture that he had to just design
نسخ من الهيكل الذي اضطر هو إلى تصميمه
one day, sort of on pencil and paper.
يوما، بورقة وقلم
And we owe a tremendous credit to that.
ونحن ندين بالكثير من الثناء لهم على ذلك
And he explained, in a very generous way,
ويشرح، بكرم شديد
the spirit that brought all these different people to
الروح التي جمعت كل هؤلاء الأشخاص
the Institute for Advanced Study in the '40s to do this project,
في المعهد لتطوير دراسات الأربعينات للعمل على هذا المشروع
and make it freely available with no patents, no restrictions,
وتوفيره مجانا دون أي حقوق، دون شروط
no intellectual property disputes to the rest of the world.
دون نزاعات على حقوق فكرية مع باقي العالم
That's the last entry in the logbook
هذا آخر مدخل في المدونة
when the machine was shut down, July 1958.
حين أطفئت الآلة في يوليو 1958
And it's Julian Bigelow who was running it until midnight
وهي من جوليان بيجالو والذي كان يديرها حتى منتصف الليل
when the machine was officially turned off.
حين أطفئت الآلة رسميا
And that's the end.
وهذه النهاية
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)